Bursting the Bubble

From a strength of 6,031 members in 200 branches at its modern peak in September 1967, the Young Communist League ended the Eighties as an extinct force, long before the end of Eastern European Communist governments. The confusion, disappointment and despair arising from all this enabled the Communist Party of Great Britain, by a majority vote in its final Congress to vote itself out of existence. But it had been bereft of a YCL for the best part of a decade earlier. How had such a situation arisen? Why a study of the YCL?

The YCL largely mirrored - sometimes in advance - the decline of the Communist Party. The "adult" body had 30,000 members in 1,200 branches in the mid-Sixties, yet entered the Nineties with less than four thousand members. The problems faced by the YCL had been the same as those faced by the Party, yet interestingly the youth organisation anticipated its "parent" body by several years in parallel circumstances. There is a sense in which the CPGB leadership "experimented" with the YCL before trying out ideas inside the Party itself. Therefore, in this case, to understand the child is to understand the parent. Not the least since many key figures in the leadership who presided over the YCL's demise, were later to become part of the Party's leadership at its very core.

This section of the CP's leadership provided much of the leadership of Democratic Left, the rump, revisionist organisation which the CPGB transformed itself into during the 1990s. This body has now voted itself out of existence, after an inglorious period of continuing to disseminate confusion. Whilst the considerable assets of the CPGB remain in the hands of a tiny element constituted as a “network” in support of “pluralist politics”! The very name of the CPGB has become purloined by a handful of strange ultra-leftist, unconnected with its illustrious namesake’s past. The historic CPGB (but not its youth wing) has now become the preserve of writers, in search of new territory for PhDs and their by-products, who rarely acknowledge the re-establishment of its finest traditions as the Communist Party of Britain. This was itself the product of attempts to prevent the Party from going the way of the YCL GB. In recent years, a renewed YCL has once again been established as the parallel youth organisation of the CPB. A study of the YCL in its final years thus repays itself for those who are interested, in a deeper understanding of the suicidal and homicidal tendencies displayed within the CPGB in its own last years.

The beginnings of the end are to be clearly identified in the 1960s. Yet this decade was a period of growth for the YCL. It would be followed by a period of intense decline in the 1970s. As a result, its 1960 membership of 1,796 was roughly equalled in 1976. The 1960s boom followed a difficult period. Membership had fallen dramatically from the 1957 figure of 3,000, reflecting the problems after the Khrushchev revelations over Stalin and the events in Hungary. A clear period of growth took place as the Communist movement began a process of recovery. By 1962 the YCL was a third larger than it had been a mere five years before and it more or less held on to the gains for a short period. But, during the course of 1965 the YCL grew by around a quarter-fold and the trend to expansion seemed to be holding steady.

YCL national membership 1957-67. Figures are for November of each year, except for October 1967.

Year | Membership
1957 | 3,000
1959 | 1,700
1960 | 1,796
1961 | 2,702
1962 | 4,019
1963 | 3,989
1965 | 4,276
1966 | 5,420
1967 | 6,031

The growing popularity of CND and the struggles of engineering apprentices contributed much to this. In retrospect 1967 was the beginning of a terminal slide to self-induced oblivion. 1966-7 was ostensibly a good period for recruitment, membership lifting by 611 from 5,420. Yet there are reasons to seriously query the accuracy of the 1967 peak, actual membership was probably just below 5,000. The issue of membership cards for that year (membership cards lasted for a calendar year and the renewal of cards was called a "card exchange" or "card issue") had been largely postal and the normal 20% turnover rate was not realistically faced up to until 1968. In this period, the CPGB tended to have a turnover rate of half that of the YCL, remarkably stable in terms of leftist political groups. (Significantly the turnover rate of the CPGB in the 1980s became very high indeed.) Paradoxically, whilst it was at its most vigorous for years that summer of 1967, the League was already in decline, but did not know it.

There are other considerations as to the accuracy of membership figures. A considerable overlap always existed between the Party and the League. Although some young communists over the minimum age of 18 years did not always also join the Party, while those that did could get counted twice in any attempt to assess the overall strength of British Communism. More relevant to the League as an organisation was that its greatest difficulty was the 'shooting star' syndrome. That is to say frequent, wild and sudden upsurges of activity as a new and enthusiastic recruit directed the pace of events at a local level. Posed against this positive, if typically youthful feature, were the big drops associated with the loss of a particularly valued cadre.

Unlike the Party, the YCL never had the luxury of a stable leadership at any level of its organisation. Perhaps this was partly due to the very nature of young people. Intensely mobile in social, geographical, occupational and personal terms as they are. Such phenomena gave rise to an uneven pace of development and/or decline in particular sectors of the organisation, accentuated most sharply in times of decline.

However, the absence of a clear policy of cadre development by both the League and the Party, coupled with an often puzzling and arbitrary - certainly inconsistent leadership policy with regard to the League by the Party contributed to instability. The CPGB often neglected the League, but it never let it range free. The Party's leadership seemed often more concerned to weed out 'oppositionalists' from the YCL, especially was this so in 'purges' of Party members from leading positions in the League in 1973 and 1975. Individuals in a number of districts were pressured to a greater or lesser degree by Party functionaries to leave the YCL, either simply in spirit or by actually leaving their League membership to lapse, in favour of predominantly or completely working inside the Party. In this sense the League was always subject to arbitrary and artificial assaults on its ability to thrive, very rarely compensated for at all, but sometimes insufficiently compensated for by the periodic thrusting of young Party members into key roles in the League, without having 'grown up' within the organisation.

Turning Rebels into Revolutionaries

The key notion of the League in the mid-Sixties was to translate the self-evident mass rebelliousness of the generation of young people then receiving a high profile in society at large, into Marxist-Leninist revolutionaries. Seizing on the mood of the times, the YCL launched its "The Trend is Communism" campaign in 1966. For which the leadership grouping became abused as being "Trendies" by the more traditional elements inside the League.

400,000 gaily-coloured folders were produced and a full-time field worker sent out into the country, to tour the coffee bars. The League planned a novel approach for its 26th National Congress due in 1967 at Skegness, in keeping with this carefully cultivated image of modernity. One thousand delegates and visitors attended what was in fact an international youth festival, grafted onto the usual Congress. There were competitions in the arts - painting, poetry, short story writing, plays, photography, cartooning, song competition, even a beat group contest. Amongst the judges were the journalist and broadcaster Malcolm Muggeridge, Arnold Wesker the playwright and Adrian Mitchell, the poet. Positive though all this undoubtedly seemed, a debt of £1,097 was left owing to the Derbyshire Miners Holiday Camp after the event, a very large sum indeed at the time. This debt was not cleared by the YCL for four years and remained a source of embarrassment for Communists active in the NUM. (To gauge the seriousness of the debt, the figure should be multiplied by at least ten times to account for inflation.)

This lively, enjoyable style began to be presented as an essential component of the League's policies. Even to the extent of YCLs in Bristol, London and Surrey organising coach trips to the seaside! The YCL in Manchester was able to get a team on 'Juke Box Jury' - a sort of forerunner of the 'Top of the Pops' - on BBC TV. Christian-Communist dialogues, debates with the Labour Party Young Socialists (LPYS) and Young Liberals, letters to the local press became a feature of YCL work. More solidly, the League also began to be deeply involved in solidarity work with other youth groups, around the issue of peace in Vietnam. The YCL launched the Medical Aid for Vietnam appeal in 1965 and was the first organisation to donate £1,000 in medical aid. Subsequently a national charity with very broad support was set up.

A Youth for Peace in Vietnam Committee, uniting 14 national youth organisations was set up, although it did not have stable, parallel organisations at regional level. Against a background of rising concern at the appalling levels of death and injury to civilians in Vietnam as the US became more actively involved in bolstering up its puppet government, the League had little difficulty in mobilising interest in its independent activities on Vietnam. The YCL organised a 'US Out Of Vietnam' petition with a target of 100,000 signatures, and planned a culmination of the campaign with a demonstration to Downing Street to present the petition to the Prime Minister, Harold Wilson. Over the same weekend another jamboree was set up in the same vein as the Skegness congress. The Round House at Chalk Farm in London was taken over for an event encompassing poetry, films, arts exhibitions, theatre, dancing, jazz, folk music and so on.

As the war progressed and the liberation forces made headway, for all the sophisticated military hardware of the USA, a wave of international resentment at the carnage emerged. Amongst young people in particular, interest in radical and revolutionary ideas grew apace. 1968 became a year famed for left-wing youthful protest. The flavour of YCL publications now took on a decidedly revolutionary, even military, character. The armed struggle as practised by Vietnam and Cuba were popular amongst many young people. Poster portraits of Che Guevara were all the rage.

The Vietnamese had always insisted that the best form of solidarity would be for Communists in the advanced capitalist nations to press for their country's disassociation from the actions of the US in Vietnam, to breach the solidarity of capitalism. Only revolutionaries would be in favour of full-bloodied victory for the liberation forces and this line - of pressing for the British (Labour!) Government's disassociation from the US - proved popular. Opinion polls by 1968 were showing two-thirds support for such a proposal. In such a climate, and with a new phase of the war entered by a general offensive of the liberation forces in 43 urban centres in Vietnam, the YCL began to feel that it was not sufficient to ask only for disassociation.

Groups that saw themselves as to the left of the CPGB/YCL did not accept this subtle approach. This saw the Medical Aid campaign as appealing to the widest sections, the disassociation campaign as building on this and the most advanced sections only being won on a position which accepted the military victory of the National Liberation Front (NLF) as the solution.

This line led to severe tensions between Communists and leftist groups. Strongly influenced by the International Marxist Group (IMG) - notable personage, Tariq Ali - and the International Socialists (IS - later Socialist Workers Party or SWP) - notable personage, Paul Foot - was the Vietnam Solidarity Campaign. This body however contained a range of radical groups, including the YCL and the CPGB National Student Committee (CPNSC). It was symptomatic of the period that the Scottish YCL congress in 1968 invited a fraternal delegate from the VSC. Even so, he was strongly criticised for over-estimating the mobilising powers of his organisation and for an under-estimation of the importance of other sections of the peace movement and the need to unite them in action.[*]

YCL Internal Bulletin, hereafter YCLIB, September 1968

An international campaign for practical and material aid to Vietnam was launched by the World Federation of Democratic Youth set up in 1945 by delegates from 63 countries in London - a sort of latter-day Comintern, without the power, of YCLs and Marxist-Leninist youth organisations throughout the world. Ultra-leftists pondered upon the possibility of a reply of the kind of international solidarity shown in Spain in the Thirties, in the form of the International Brigades. Communists were more realistic and asked the Vietnamese what they needed. Foreign volunteers, untrained in jungle warfare and unfamiliar with the territory, the people and their language and culture, was the last thing required.

Material aid in the struggle was however crucial. The WFDY campaign - entitled "Victory to the Vietnamese People for their Freedom, Independence and Peace" - was geared to raising money for the purchase of particular, militarily useful commodities, difficult to get hold of in war-torn Vietnam. Bicycles were a popular item to purchase, being easy to acquire in the west, yet possessing an unimaginable strategic value on the jungle trails. Supply lines from the more conventional warfare zones were very extended. To get medicines, food, ammunition and so on to the underground in US dominated areas was a very difficult task. Everything had to go by foot, so the bicycles, stripped down, were very useful as transporters of goods. But there was also a need for cameras, radios, typewriters and even motorcycles.

The YCL entered this campaign with considerable gusto at all levels, and often brought considerable imagination to fund-raising as well as vigour. Leeds YCL bought rolls of cloth which would make uniforms for the NLF, Bristol and SE London aimed for a £250 motorbike each. Bletchley aimed for two transistor radios, Hatfield and Luton for a walkie-talkie set each, Stevenage for a field operation kit. There were scores and scores of bicycles - Dundee YCL for example bought 5, Coventry 3.

Newcastle, which had been dormant for six months, collected £90, Bristol £80, Coventry £26, Manchester £30, Dundee £81, Croydon £30 - each of them in less than the first eight weeks. Eventually over £6,500 was raised and perhaps as a measure of the relative worth of this amount it would be well to bear in mind that a wage of £15 to £20 a week would considered very acceptable to most people at this time.

A lorry was bought with which to collect all these items in a round-Britain celebratory tour. Over June 14th to July 19th 1968 a couple of dozen locations were visited. These were:

Newcastle
Stockton
Hull
Leeds
Sheffield
Liverpool
Manchester
Nottingham
Leicester
Wolverhampton
Coventry
Birmingham
Scotland
Luton
Wales
Bristol
Oxford
Southampton
Brighton
Chatham
London

The campaign partially climaxed in a 15,000 strong demonstration on July 21 supported by 17 national organisations. While the material was transported by bus across Europe to Bulgaria, the YCL’s lorry having now become a write-off as a result of a road traffic accident. A second hand bus was secured as a replacement and, once safely there, the goods were presented, along with the aid from other WFDY affiliates, in symbolic ceremonies at the World Youth Festival then underway in the capital, Sofia. It was reported at the 27th Congress that a shipment of over £4,000 of goods had gone to Vietnam.

However, without doubt, the culmination of the victory for Vietnam campaign was the October 27th 1968 demonstration. The YCL and the CPNSC participated with the VSC, IS, the Young Liberals and the British Peace Committee (a body strongly influenced by the Party which campaigned on questions of international security) in the October 27th Ad Hoc Committee - the only degree of unity feasible. Despite the provocative and irrational actions of a tiny number of Maoist-led demonstrators, which received significant press and media attention, some 250,000 marched peacefully in London. Rather stupid suggestions that this was the signal for a leftist putsch emanated from the gutter press, yet this was the biggest protest since the war probably, certainly since Suez.

The atmosphere generated by all this, particularly the YCL's own solidarity campaign, laid the basis for much potential growth. 150 of the YCL's 200 branches took part in the campaign and no less than 323 applications for membership were received nationally during this period. This was very important for the YCL, which had begun to appreciate severe membership problems.

The YCL saw the 1967-68 card exchange, as Colin Yardley reported to the YCL National Committee (NC) in March 1968, as a serious set-back for us. The League's 200 branches were in 19 Districts, all but three of which had functioning District Committees. Comparing these to the last non-postal card issue, nine districts were up in membership, three were about the same and seven had suffered a loss. The two biggest districts, London and Scotland, had experienced severe losses.

Nationally, the drop in 1966 was 16%, by 1968 it was 29%. Two year's losses almost had been collected in one year. Moreover, this was part of a long-term trend. There had not been a 100% result in the card issue for nine years, while the Average Dues Paying Membership (ADPM) - the value of membership stamps bought by districts from centre divided by official membership figures - was only 24% in 1967. The YCL congress felt obliged to note that "the decision to post cards to members has created more problems than it has solved".

At the start of the card issue, the League noted in December 1967 that many districts have reported losses through people going into the Party, through people moving and leaving no forwarding address. So far only a tiny amount of direct political losses have been reported. It was thought that recruits could replace every loss. If members are lost, then they must be replaced by new members. Every branch was very strongly urged to achieve 100% membership. Anything less, wrote Barney Davis, the National Secretary of the YCL, is not just a loss to the branch but a loss to the whole communist movement.[*]

YCLIB No3 December 1967

There was thus a contradictory, confused yet still largely positive position. New branches were being formed all the time. Ebbw Vale, Bristol (Lawrence Weston), Balham, Barnsley, Dover, Hemel Hempstead, Wigan, Sale and several in Scotland were all reported as being set up by January 1968. While there were a number of branches making large numbers of recruits: - Mansfield 13, Bristol 22, Catford 15, St Pancras 13, Newham 12, Hampstead 12 and Edinburgh 60.

Birmingham YCL had an explosion of branches, 6 or 7 being set up out of one in no time at all, although it turned out that there was not a sufficiently strong basis for these. They were not maintained long and soon disintegrated back into the one. The YCL in Birmingham finished the card issue with 109 members, having made 20 recruits during the campaign. The district - the Midlands YCL - achieved 330 members by April 1st and was recruiting 20 new members per month. A district target of 600 members in 30 branches might have been ambitious, but it did not seem unnecessarily unrealistic, even if later such targets became mechanical ambitions, from sheer enthusiasm. After all branches were springing up all over the place in the Midlands, as elsewhere.

In January a Mid-Warwickshire branch was formed, based on Leamington and Rugby. In June, two branches of 10 members each were set up in Wolverhampton. A branch of 10 was established in Lichfield, which began working in Tamworth, Burton -on-Trent and Walsall, where there was a small group of five members needing encouragement. The aim of setting up a South Staffordshire organisation was decided upon.

Groups emerged in the smallest of towns - Stourbridge (8 members), Worcester (8), Hereford (14). Political activity naturally reflected this mathematical increase. A Midlands YCL district school in the spring of 1968 on the Party's programme, the

British Road to Socialism

, was organised with the expectation of getting some 45 in attendance, in the event 65 turned up! Three members of Birmingham YCL were involved in the Youth Parliament, an establishment body which involved a very wide range of youth organisations. Wolverhampton YCL was selling 50 copies of the YCL's paper,

Challenge

, in the first half of 1968, but 400 in July.

In the East Midlands, 25 delegates to the YCL's 4th District Congress in 1967 heard how membership had rocketed from 127 in 1965 to 230 in 1967 in 7 new branches. Though how much of this reflected the postal card issue is naturally a factor to be born in mind.

At the 26th National Congress there had been much concern at the position in Wales, traditionally a strong area for Communism - in the mining valleys at least. In the Sixties it had become a "very weak area and on the verge of collapse" for the YCL. More positive was the fact that the Welsh YCL had been able to organise a weekend school with 12 present from 4 branches, the average age of those attending being 19 years 2 months.*

YCLIB September 1967

A little late in the day, the North East YCL was reformed in 1970, but rapidly doubled membership and tripled Challenge sales, with new branches at Darlington and Sunderland. The West of England District Congress held in September 1968 was the first for 12 years. During the course of that year the district had achieved the fastest rate of growth of any. There were now 93 members, 60 of whom were recent recruits. Bristol Central YCL was selling 600 Challenge - enormous for a branch of about 20 members. The 20 delegates at the congress came from 5 branches in this widely scattered, largely rural district.

Yorkshire YCL was 267 strong in 1966, but mushroomed to 422 in the following year, with three branches alone in Leeds. South East Midlands doubled in size in one year, reaching nine branches. The Scottish YCL Congress in May 1968 was attended by 76 delegates from 24 branches, together with some 30 odd consultative and fraternal delegates, yet this represented a weaker position than the previous congress two and a half years before. Then there had been 100 delegates. This reflected a severe organisation weakness, akin to that experienced by Wales. 500 members had been lost and the full-time YCL District Secretary's position was reduced to that of a part-timer. (Doug Bain had been the full-timer from 1963 to 1968, Andy Sweeney was the part-time replacement.)

The Scottish YCL spent the next couple of years grappling with what was essentially a financial problem. The League, perhaps like the Party, in Scotland had real and popular support in some areas, but translating what was often a family, almost tribal, commitment into organised activity was another matter. Both the Midlands and the Yorkshire YCLs planned full-timers, but only the latter was able to achieve this by creating a full-time post which was in fact jointly part-time with the Yorkshire Communist Party. Generally it was only through such mechanisms that the YCL could fund district full-timers. Whilst the CPGB part-funded the YCL nationally by means of a "grant", the districts were obliged to raise their own finances and usually were only treated to implicit subsidy by the Party, perhaps for example by writing off literature debts to CP owned bookshops.

Like the Party, the League saw left unity as being built to the extent to which the CPGB and the YCL grew in size and influence. The paramount task is to lay the basis for the immediate and rapid growth of the Young Communist League … The revolutionary character of every young communist must now be tested by his or her part in achieving the 4,000 membership in this 1970 card exchange. This was how the YCL national leadership put it, just as it became clear that the 1968 bubble had burst. [*] Motivating much of the YCL's work was a belief in the special revolutionary character of youth. As George Bridges put it: Youth are free from reformist illusions. They develop new uninhibited forms of activity immediately corresponding with their mood.[*] This concept underlay a blind faith that mass membership was there to be won and it would only take hard work to achieve it.

YCLIB January 1970

George Bridges August 1969 Marxism Today

Size became an all-important feature of the League's work and as the organisation did not gear itself to consistent long-term work, immediate startling publicity became the most sought-after objective. That is to say, imaginative events that attracted national, establishment media attention. Bob Allen, London YCL District Secretary, and Tony McNally, YCL National Organiser, late in 1969 protested outside a seminar of British generals against their suggestion to re-introduce conscription, in such a way that Fleet Street took notice. With membership at 3,686 in November 1969 - 2,300 down on the 1967 position, a thousand down on 1968 - the League began to become more than a little concerned. The number of branches was down to 181 in April 1969.

The aim of 4,000 members was established as a supposedly realistic benchmark and 100,000 recruitment leaflets produced, as the organisation set itself to remedying the problem. But there were serious internal difficulties that were in part a product of long-term decline, but were also largely the cause of fundamental damage to the organisation in the 1970s. These arose out of the sharpening political differences which were to, as Doug Chalmers, the then YCL General Secretary put it at the 1983 CPGB Congress, to paralyse the work of League.* These differences were eventually treated in so fractious a manner as to cause outright personal hostility between individuals of such a character that the work of the organisation was de-stabilised. But it was not always so.

Author's personal contemporary notes

Amongst the tutors at a YCL national school in October 1967 were Sid French and Eric Trevett, the Surrey full-timers for the Party, long-time critics of the BRS's programme of parliamentary transition without civil war and eventual first and second leaders of the breakaway New Communist Party. Their presence at the school ensured that the discussion thrived and even became heated. In fact … it was generally felt that some of the tutors were more 'off the line' than the students, commented the YCL's internal bulletin rather mildly. Such a possibility—of major dissidents lecturing a national cadre school—would later become unthinkable.[*]

YCLIB December 1967

Dissent was tolerated sufficiently for one participant on a 40 strong YCL organised holiday trip to the Soviet Union to comment in the bulletin in the following terms. There were no holds barred in our talks and our Russian hosts spoke freely about issues on which their country has been heavily criticised in the West… on the question of the treatment of the Jews in the Soviet Union, which was raised in a British Communist Party statement, they (i.e. the Soviets) were all agreed that our party had been duped by capitalist press reports. [*]

YCLIB December 1967 - article by Mike Ambrose

There would be little of such comment—other than in a letter printed to reveal the quirkiness of the dissidents—in YCL publications in the 1970s and beyond. Articles sympathetic to the Soviet Union would be excluded as 'not being of interest to young people' and individuals who differed with the League leadership on these questions would find themselves excluded from leadership roles. Some YCLers adopted pro-soviet views that conflicted with reality as even seen by the Communist Party of the Soviet Union, but the process of squeezing fundamentalist assessments out of the League even inhibited balanced—and accurate—analyses and reinforced a cynical but vigorous anti-Sovietism in the leadership.

The Party and the League had of course been no strangers to political dissent, particularly arising from the need to protect the organisation from outside interference and policies. There had been a brief period of Trotskyist involvement in some YCL branches when the Socialist Labour League (later Gerry Healey's Workers' Revolutionary Party - WRP) had infiltrated cadres. Then the split between China and the Soviet Union had resulted in the whole new tendency of Maoism, which actively sought to split and infiltrate Communist movements. The YCL had its share of trouble from these quarters. There had been plenty of tensions and differences before, over major policy questions, but minority opinions had usually been minuscule. Most of those who had left over Hungary had done simply that, resigned or lapsed from membership. Factionalism, whether informal or semi-organised, had not been strongly evident in British Communism for the bulk of its existence. (Early Trotskyite internal dissent had been marginal.) So the ruthless crushing of different views inside the organisation, by ostracising large numbers of branches or even whole Districts, had not been an obvious feature of Party life. The much publicised prohibition, a decade before, of Party members such as Edward Thompson from publishing a non-Party journal, the New Reasoner, had led to a small number leaving to involve themselves in the New Left. No leadership led wholesale purge of dissent had ever occurred and there had been little need for administrative action to silence critics. There had been differences of course, largely at leadership level and consequently much internalised, and these had often been debated with sharpness, but personal vindictiveness was not a hallmark of the CPGB/YCL at that stage.

As J R Campbell had told the Comintern functionary, Manuilsky, it is not the tradition of the British Communist Party to divide the Party into goats and sheep. Manuilsky replied by comparing unfavourably the British Communists with the Germans who allowed no deviation from the line, they attack the least deviation, respect no persons… Yet in the British Communist Party there is a sort of special system which may be characterised thus: the Party is a society of great friends…[*] What went for the Party in a traditional sense also went for the YCL of course.

Noreen Branson "History of the Communist Party of Great Britain 1927-1941" pp45-6 (1985).

However, questions of democracy in socialist countries, attitudes to errors and distortions, controversies, differences in social, historical or political traditions between the western liberal-democratic style and the rather more basic aspirations of second and third world peoples, all became highly significant debating points in the YCL. Indeed in the Party also, even if the latter took a more restrained view of things.

Without doubt, the single most significant happening in this period, which forced along the pace of division inside the YCL, was the Warsaw Pact intervention in Czechoslovakia in 1968. The YCL immediately distinguished itself as having a sharper line than the Party did. The CPGB characterised the affair as an "intervention"; the YCL preferred the more emotive "invasion". The Party sedately called for district aggregates to debate the matter behind closed doors in sombre, thoughtful discussions. The Midlands aggregate was enlivened by a call from one of the leading YCLers of the time, later a pillar of the Birmingham Labour Party, for the CP's resignation from the Comintern, which had of course been dissolved in 1943!

The YCL leadership saw their position as more clear-cut, less a case of debating the matter in the branches as "Fighting For The Line", as a series of articles in the Internal Bulletin put it. Moreover, for the League it was less a case of making careful condemnatory press statements concentrating on matters of high diplomatic and international legal principles and tenets, and much more a case of campaigning to distance the organisation from the Soviet Union. An Emergency National Committee of the YCL decided to organise a series of public meetings in solidarity with Czechoslovakia - or at any rate Dubcek's Czechoslovakia.

Challenge

came out with a front cover irreverently and irrelevantly decorated by a psychedelically dressed young woman who informed the reader that: If you think Communism means that tanks can roll in at anytime, you're bloody wrong.[*]

Magazine Series: Issue No 9.

Nonetheless more weighty matters had to be borne in mind at the 27th National Congress of the YCL in Scarborough in April 1969, when the policy of the League had to be put to the test. Despite the distortions of popular myth in the YCL in the 1970s, the conflicting positions actually voted on at the Congress were not baldly for or against the actions of the USSR and its allies. The National Committee's sharp characterisation of the affair as an invasion was actually faced with an alternative position of opposition to the events on the basis of international communist principles. An alternative motion from Harrow supported the Communist Party of Czechoslovakia and the other Warsaw Pact powers, on the basis of their statement after the events of the summer of 1968. This jointly agreed Czech-Soviet position largely affirmed much of the demands in the NC resolution for a spirit of harmony. There was no simple choice - oppose the 'intervention/invasion' or support it, for the congress reflected the more complex realities of Communist life. Many, on all sides, later reflecting on that Congress simply forgot that.

The policy of the League on Czechoslovakia was increasingly seen as a totem, perhaps even to the extent that the actual nature of the policy was less relevant than its observance. For the CPGB, the whole issue was a question of a fundamental and principled difference over the nature of territorial integrity between socialist states. This was a difficult question for believers in world socialism. Strictly speaking, differences over the question need not necessarily colour other areas of work. Yet, for the YCL, attitudes to Czechoslovakia became a substitute for support or otherwise of the concept of a mass League; i.e. a YCL of size and influence working for socialism within the BRS's tactics and strategy.

Differences in the League over the mass YCL concept actually became confused as positions polarised. London full-timer for the YCL, Laureen Mason (later Hickey) put it well. While complaining about the eternal labelling of individuals in one camp or another (a case of goats and sheep?), she argued that it is possible for instance for a member to believe the Soviet Union were correct about Czechoslovakia but still play a positive role in the league.[*] Others in the YCL's leadership thought differently.

YCL Pre-Congress Discussion Document 1971

Indeed, there is a sense in which Czechoslovakia became a matter almost of obsession to the leadership of the YCL, exceeding the relevance of the issue to young people in a continuing way far into the 1970's. At its crudest, the obsession was based on a simple belief that the events of 1968 had cost the League its popularity. That the membership problems which soon emerged in a most obvious way were inter-linked somehow with a juxtaposition of the '68 spirit. YCL national leader for nearly all of the next decade, Tom Bell, made his view clear as early as 1970. The invasion of Czechoslovakia set us back more than we realise. Thousands of young rebels who could have been won to the YCL were turned to Ultra-Leftism and cynicism, they less than ever looked to the Soviet Union for inspiration.[*] Bell made a similar point in the YCLIB in January 1971 concerning death sentences, albeit subsequently withdrawn, of would-be Jewish plane hijackers. The affair had received hysterical press condemnation and the whole was assessed by Bell thus: our struggle has been made harder.

Cogito No1 1970 "Time for Change

The League issued statement after statement on Czechoslovakia, following events there with dogged persistence. After the congress had endorsed the NC's position, the leadership issued a statement in September 1969. There was another in April 1970, expressing concern at the Czech Party disciplining Dubček and his associates. (This statement was endorsed by the NC on a vote of 15 to 5, with one abstention.) There was another in March 1971, another in August 1972, and another in October 1976. The latter statement was in protest at trials of rock musicians in Prague. In a calculated rebuff to the Czech YCL (the SSM, or Czechoslovak Socialist Youth Movement), it was decided not to actually go so far as to sever normal relations with that organisation but to refuse the offer of exchange delegations. Another statement came out in February 1977, when the YCL decided to look into the possibility of affiliating to Amnesty International. The tenth anniversary of the 1968 events was marked by the YCL by a special statement and an article in

Challenge

- most YCL members by that stage would have been in primary school when the Dubček government was in power.

Differences of the kind experienced by the YCL occurred in other countries, although these, where they were exaggerated by special conditions, could explode into splits which in turn posed problems for fraternal organisations. For example, which grouping to support?

In common with the vast majority of Communist Parties and Youth Leagues in the world, the British Party and YCL were estranged from the Chinese during the Sixties. The Chinese YCL representative at Budapest to the World Federation of Democratic Youth was "withdrawn" as the YCL Internal Bulletin put it, rather ominously perhaps. Like most YCLs, the British organisation had "some difficulty" in locating the Chinese YCL, refusing to recognise the Red Guards as a formal organisation, so the YCLGB simply lost touch. Concern over maintaining relations noticeably rose in the early 1970s, as the tensions over Czechoslovakia mounted, the leadership grew more anxious to prove that it was not coat-tailing Moscow by appearing open-minded over China. In 1970 the YCL felt impelled to specifically state that for its forthcoming Congress fraternal delegates from overseas be invited, including Chinese.[*] Although this was later qualified to make it clear that such a Chinese organisation be the Communist youth organisation if it existed.[*]

YCLIB 18th November 1970

YCL 28th Congress documents 1971

In Australia, the Communist Party and YCL moved rapidly through Maoist and Trotskyist influences, only to find much of the trade union base of the movement splitting off after major expulsions into the Socialist Party of Australia and the Young Socialist League of Australia - seen as new replacement Marxist-Leninist organisations. The YCL in Britain had no difficulty in refusing to recognise the YSL in August 1974, despite the appearance of representatives of that body at WFDY meetings. Interestingly, the Australian Communist Party, at this stage certainly, preferred an analysis of the socialist states as being "post capitalist societies" or "socialist based".

In Greece, differences over the conduct of the anti-fascist struggle against the army junta then in control, merged with international controversies inside the Communist movement. Two Communist parties and youth organisations emerged, but here - partially because of certain strong links with the British Party on the part of both groups - the CPGB decided to maintain relations with both. The YCL was loath to follow such a course, having strong political allegiances to the revisionist student movement, Rigeos Ferros - which was what later would be called the Euro-Communist tendency. The Communist Youth of Greece (KNE) had many contacts in London, not the least through the strong Cypriot presence there - a presence which had always been dominated by Communists. The YCLGB decided in June 1975 to keep contacts with both groups in line with the CPGB's position, but the League was cool with the KNE at national level, while the 'opposition' in the YCL was very much taken with it.

Increasingly, the YCL found itself isolated along with a group, mainly west European, at WFDY meetings which was distant and cool with the majority. Questions of Soviet policy were seen by this minority group as prime matters of concern. In consequence of the minority with which the Italians, Spanish, British, Japanese and others found themselves they began to query the role of WFDY.

The periodic world gatherings of WFDY were every five years, with a general council meeting yearly in between. Mike Power, the British delegate to the 8th World Assembly in 1971, reported to the YCL that WFDY "had never really become a broad all embracing youth movement" and that there seemed "very little likelihood of it doing so". He felt WFDY to be "following a tired pattern". WFDY's recognition of both Greek youth movements was seen by him as "support to splitting activities". Moreover, the insistence of the majority of organisations in WFDY that the notion of peaceful "co-operation" between states be included in a statement on European security irked Power. Because of this he complained that it was "hard to decide whether the Assembly is a gathering of international youth against imperialism, or a meeting of young diplomats". Power saw the fight for European security as "a class battle and part of the struggle for socialism".* Rather ironically, the early 1980s debate about the direction the Party should take was initially and partially symbolically centred on whether peace is a class issue or a democratic issue. Mike Power subsequently became the editor of the short-lived Democratic Left's even shorter-lived journal

New Times

.

YCL NC Minutes January 2/3 1971

World Youth Festivals

The most significant role of WFDY was to organise the massive cultural and political festivals held periodically in differing parts of the world. There have been 12 Festivals: Prague (1947), Budapest (1949), Berlin (1951), Bucharest (1953), Warsaw (1955), Moscow (1957), Vienna (1959), Helsinki (1962), Sofia (1968), Berlin (1973), Cuba (1978), and Moscow (1983) A festival usually had around sixteen thousand participants at it, although the 1973 Berlin Festival touched 26,000. From the original 63 founding countries of WFDY, it had affiliates from 72 countries at its first festival and 112 by the 1959 Vienna event. These festivals aimed to involve youth organisations other than of the Communists and were moreover always spectacular in character - a memorable event in each generation's experience.

Some 14 organisations were involved in the Sofia 1968 British Preparatory Committee, the link up with the Vietnam campaign making this possible. Organisations like the Young Liberals, Young Oxfam and the Student Christian Movement joined up with the YCL in sending some 300 delegates to Bulgaria. The League saw this as an especially important development for its work in Britain. So much so that it approached the 1973 Berlin Festival with great plans for massive broad youth unity in the British Preparatory Committee, one thousand delegates were aimed for. Already, the previous year, a Vietnam Youth Committee had been set up under the auspices of the British Campaign for Peace in Vietnam. This brought together the National Union of Students (NUS), the Young Liberals, the Amalgamated Union of Engineering Workers (Technical and Supervisory Staffs) (AUEW/TASS), the United Nations Youth and Students Association and of course the YCL. All of these organisations and others were easily won to involvement in the World Youth Festival, the NUS being a particularly important body. The NUS had supported the 1947 Youth Festival, but had not done so since due to governmental and other pressures associated with the cold war.

Apart from some tensions within the British delegation arising out of the presence of a Gay Liberation banner, the whole event did much to break down barriers artificially erected by the cold war. (The banner had been rather frowned upon by the East Germans, but supported vigorously on a point of principle by both the Young Liberals and the YCL national leadership, perhaps with tactical considerations back home being very much in the collective mind of the latter.) Major changes in the official youth movement in Britain were on their way. Together with the positive gains of the Berlin Festival, these laid the basis for even more significant unity. The main resolution at the YCL's 29th Congress in 1973 saw "the preparations (as) an example of the broad youth unity, albeit embryonic" that it sought generally in Britain.

Of tremendous significance for the next World Youth Festival after Berlin was the disaffiliation of the British Youth Council (BYC) from WFDY's cold war rival, the World Assembly of Youth (WAY). This was to open up the possibility of much wider involvement in youth unity activities. It had become public knowledge that WAY had been at least partially funded by the CIA for much of its life and the BYC's links with that body grew more and more tenuous. The BYC itself had been set up in 1949 and it was funded by various British government departments, as well as by the subscriptions of the affiliated organisations. These included such groups as the Boy Scouts, Girl Guides, Boys’ Brigades, Young Farmers, Young Conservatives and a variety of Christian youth organisations, as well as the Labour Party Young Socialists and the Young Liberals. In 1976, with the link with WAY now dissolved, the YCL and other progressive organisations like the Co-operative movement's Woodcraft Folk, the NUSS and the National Organisation of Labour Students (NOLS) all decided to affiliate to the BYC. At his first attempt, Tom Bell narrowly failed to obtain election to the executive committee of the BYC.

Preparations for the 11th World Youth Festival, to be held from Friday 28th July to Saturday 5th August, were already underway and it was clear that, especially with it being held in Cuba, that there would have to be a tremendous effort to avoid the massive organisational and travelling difficulties. Indeed the Festival was put back a year to allow for all of this. 23,000 delegates - 18,500 from outside Cuba - from 145 countries were expected, along with 1,000 journalists. There were 3,200 from West Europe, 800 from Africa, 3,800 from the Americas, 1,600 from Asia, 800 from the Middle East, 1,000 from the USSR, 750 from the GDR (East Germany) and 3,050 from East Europe. After an initial expectation of a higher number, it eventually became clear that the British delegation would only number 180 and it would cost £310 to send each one.

The BYC agreed to participate in the Festival on the understanding that the British Preparatory Committee would support the right of its individual member groups to raise whatever issues they wished and that the BPC itself raise certain issues of controversy with respect to democracy in socialist states. The BYC was under great pressure before the event from the Federation of Conservative Students and the Young Conservatives to withdraw its support, indeed these groups themselves refused to participate. Even so, several Tories remained on the delegation as representatives of the Churches, in particular in the Methodist camp. While the Foreign Office refused to give a £5,000 grant for a cultural delegation from Britain.

The NUS was to play a particularly important part in this BPC. Charles Clarke, who had recently been the National President of the NUS, landed the job of permanent British representative in Havana for a year before the Festival. While the leader of the delegation was Trevor Phillips, 24 year old NUS President. His deputy was Peter Mandelson, noted then only for being personally related to the former Labour Home Secretary, Herbert Morrison and tipped, like Phillips, to go on to greater things. (Mandelson had been a member of the London YCL for about nine months in the early 1970s.)

For both of these the whole affair was an important test. As the Sunday Telegraph, rather bluntly put it, "both plan careers in mainstream politics, and Mr Mandelson felt that a heavily Stalinist British contribution in Havana could have serious career repercussions for him. Messrs Phillips and Mandelson, therefore, were determined that Britain would raise the issue of human rights." \[Sunday Telegraph August 6th 1978\] In particular, they planned that leaflets on the status of Soviet dissidents, Shcharansky and Orlov, should be distributed at the Festival. Mandelson, of course, notoriously became Labour's key media man under the Kinnock leadership; Clarke was the key figure in Kinnock's personal political advisory team. Phillips went on to become a TV producer and occasional presenter. All three ended up as key figures in the Blair project.

In a heavy-handed move of supremely unconscious irony, the BPC leadership decided to rid itself of any delegates who would be too obviously opposed to the plan to seek publicity for an anti-Soviet position. What involvement there was on the part of the YCL in the original calculations remains undefined, but how else could the non-communist leadership of the BPC be aware of identity of the most outspoken Communists hoping to be part of the delegation? Who told Phillips and Mandelson which were the key people to exclude? Whatever the position, seven CPGB and NCP members were literally banned from going to Cuba. Trevor Phillips, as Chair of the BPC, and Tom Bell, as its Secretary, wrote to at least three of these who then made the whole affair public. They were Dave Smith (ASTMS), Will Gee (FBU) and Lysandras Lysandrou (United Cypriot Youth Organisation - EKON).

They were told that there were travel difficulties and that as they were nominated by organisations not in membership of the BPC and that the "trade union section of the delegation is already fairly heavily subscribed to" it was not possible to accept their nomination. More decisively, and the strongest clue to where the objections were coming from, "it has been questioned by a member organisation of the BPC whether your approach to the Festival, given the basis of your past political record and activity would be entirely in line with the tenets and spirit of British participation in the Festival, as agreed and delineated by the British Preparatory Committee". \[Letter dated 14th July 1978\] Which "member organisation" was not publicly revealed, but clearly non-communists could only be aware of what was essentially a criticism of their differences with the YCL's line on socialist democracy from the YCL leadership.

After receiving the Phillips-Bell letter, two of the excluded met with the BPC's organising committee and offered to travel by other means, if travelling was the problem. The committee voted by 3 to 1 not to reverse their exclusion - leaving the matter of their political suitability as the key objection. A simple reference to the balance of the delegation reveals a high proportion of students and a rather small trade union delegation.

Student Bodies |
National Union of Students | 38
National Union of School Students | 1
Communist Party National Students Committee | 3
National Organisation of Labour Students | 3
Student Christian Movement | 4

Trade Unions

AUEW/TASS (engineering workers and staff)                     4
ACTT  (cinema technicians)                                              1
EEPTU (electricians)                                                        1
ASTMS (managers/technicians)                                        2
NUT (teachers)                                                                4
NUPE (public employees)                                                2
NUM (miners)                                                                  5
AUEW (engineers)                                                           1
AUT (university lecturers)                                                 1
TGWU (transport & general)                                             5
NATFHE (college lecturers)                                              1
NALGO (local government)                                              1
APEX (clerical workers)                                                               1
Greater London Association of Trades Councils                1
Haringey Trades Council                                                  1

Community and Miscellaneous Bodies

Returned Volunteer Action                                 1
Melting Pot Foundation                                                 1
British Council of Churches - Youth Unit                         4
CBSLC (identity unknown to author)                   1
British Preparatory Committee                            10
Young Farmers                                                             1
BLF (identity unknown to author)                        1
Legal Staffs Association                                   1
National Assembly of Women                            1
National Film School                                         1
Afro-Caribbean Education Resource Project       1
Community Service Volunteers                           1
Jubilee Hall Recreation Centre                            1
National Association of Indian Youth                  1
Southall Youth Movement                                  2
Indian Youth Association                                   2
EKON (Cypriot Youth)                                       2
RCA Film School                                               1
Woodcraft FoIk (Co-op)                                     1
Cultural Delegation                                           8
Young Friends (Quakers)                                   1
Women in Manual Trades Group                         1
National Association of Youth Clubs                  1
British Youth Council (BYC)                               5

Campaigning and Political Bodies

YCL                                                                                          16
Labour Party                                                                 2
LPYS                                                                            4
Young Liberals                                                              4
Campaign Against Youth Unemployment (CAYU)            1
Anti-Apartheid Movement                                               1
Chile Solidarity Campaign                                              1
Young European Left                                                    1
Namibia Support Committee                                         1
Namibia International Peace Centre                                 1
African National Congress                                             1

SUMMARY

Category                                               No.                   %

Student Bodies                         49                     30
Trade Unions                             31                     19
Political/Campaigning                34                     21
Community/Miscellaneous         49                     30
Total                                        163                   100

Given that travelling was not really the problem, although there were difficulties these were not insurmountable, and that if any group needed thinning down it was the student element of the delegation, how could the BPC's banning of the dissident element be justified? The community sector could not lend itself to reduction, as there were generally only one or two delegates per group. If the TGWU with two million members could be easily represented by 5 delegates, how could it be that the NUS with perhaps half or a third of that number needed 38 delegates? In truth, delegates were often simply people who had both the interest and the money to pay. Their sponsoring organisation had simply endorsed them as delegates, at no cost to the organisation. Apart from measures to ensure that each single organisation was at least once represented, very little tinkering with the overall delegation was really necessary. Therefore, there could only seriously remain the matter of the political objection. Two of the excluded delegates produced statements, revealing the full details of the affair, including copies of the correspondence. They declared that the BYC had given an ultimatum to the BPC to veto the likes of them and that they had been removed for political reasons "without any opportunity to reply to the allegations." In the Morning Star, Reuben Falber for the CPGB was pressed by their statement to publicly respond for the Party that it understood travel problems. But that it was regrettable that, in making the difficult decisions to thin down the delegation, it was implied that some were excluded because of their politics.

Bob Lentell, speaking for the YCL as its National Organiser, made a similar point as Falber over the travel arrangements question. But the YCL had disagreements on some parts of the festival preparations and felt that the BPC, having laid down its political principles at an early stage, had the right to ensure "that the British delegation adhered to these principles". Implicit in this was some degree of sympathy for the exclusions.

Tom Bell, in a subsequent article on the Festival in Challenge, conceded that the BPC "didn't handle every question as well as it might have done", but thought on balance the Festival overall was a positive development. While the exclusion of some people was not "handled in the best way" and some should have gone, Bell supported the right of the BPC to make the decision. \[Challenge No 55 1978\]

For the vast majority of delegates the first they knew of the controversy was when they arrived in Cuba. The statements of the excluded two, together with the copies of correspondence were distributed in large numbers by their sympathisers amongst the delegation. After protracted arguments a delegation meeting at the large, modern teacher training college six kilometres from Havana, which the British shared with the Irish, Scandinavian and Low Countries delegations, passed a decisive resolution to bring over three individuals excluded from the delegation. Clive Haswell of the Welsh Preparatory Committee - two of the excluded were Welsh - moved that the steering committee running affairs in Cuba amongst the delegation be instructed to reverse the ban and make arrangements to get the three to the Festival.

It had been necessary to propose a procedural motion to discuss the matter, despite an attempt by the steering committee to avoid this. Then the motion was narrowly passed.  Once the issues were debated the delegation voted 84 for the critical motion 50 against. It should be noted that 73 of the delegation were either absent or abstained. The decision was of course largely symbolic, the meeting being held on the first day of the Festival at 1pm on Friday 28th August, but it was symptomatic of a large gap between the steering committee and the delegation majority. The three never got to the Festival of course.

This affair rather conditioned the atmosphere on the delegation and attitudes to the leadership of the steering committee, in particular the determination of Mandelson and Phillips to issue a delegation statement on human rights. A document, which bore all the hallmarks of a rushed and thoughtless composition, especially in the circumstances that the delegation now found itself, suddenly appeared. Very little consultation with very few people had prefaced its appearance, which drew much criticism. It was ill conceived and almost calculated to annoy most Communists.

Bell, in his subsequent Challenge article, conceded that "while some delegates wanted more time to discuss the contents of the statement, a minority were determined to prevent it being issued at all … given the sectarian, Stalinist positions they held they were not prepared to accept any criticisms of the Soviet Union or other socialist countries.”

The Sunday Telegraph reckoned that about half of the delegation – something like 80 odd people – were Communists, and their views varied. Many supported the CPGB’s position on socialist democracy, but were unhappy with the ease with which some allowed unbalanced positions to be postulated by the delegation leadership. Many, perhaps 30 to 40, were committed to one or another of the tendencies inside the British Communist movement, which repudiated the official position on these matters. An alliance between the two elements, winning support amongst the trade union and some Labour and progressive groupings, ensured that the delegation was deeply split.

Some, especially those associated with anti-imperialist causes like Ireland, were strongly opposed even to the notion of carrying the Union Flag ahead of the British delegation's representatives on the opening ceremony's 'walk past'. While the discovery that the official, identifying T-shirts bore the Festival logo coloured in with the Union Flag created some controversy. Those who objected argued that the flag was associated in half of the world with bloody imperialism, a force which the Festival was specifically in opposition to. Those who favoured the Union Flag simply viewed it as the nation's official emblem, which was known to all.

With all this, it is not surprising perhaps that the draft statement on human rights was greeted with hostility. Moreover, there was a time constraint that led to a feeling that the steering committee was trying to rush things. The BPC wanted the statement ready for a particular commission on the first Monday of the Festival. Despite an attempt to block the statement completely, the delegation voted to discuss the draft and to amend it by a vote of 64 to 60. (Noticeably, as the controversy raged, fewer and fewer people participated in the delegation meetings.) 30 to 40 delegates then walked out to draft an alternative statement. The remainder, including many who differed with much of the intent, tone and content of the originating statement determined to change it.

From 6.00 p.m. on Sunday 30th to 4.00 am on Monday 31st, during successive, strained and marathon sessions at the delegation’s lodgings, the statement was hotly debated and amended. The initial session by 6.30 p.m. had agreed on the go-ahead. Then the YCL EC members met with the CPNSC members - as no doubt did other caucuses - drafting amendments which were in the main agreed to by the delegation leadership and, subsequently, the majority of the delegation as a whole, in a midnight to four am meeting.

The original statement linked the Helsinki Declaration on Human Rights to détente, arguing that concern over human rights did not sabotage the fight for peace. Central to all this was the freedom of speech and assembly. Concern was expressed about the 1968 events in Czechoslovakia and the more recent experience of the Charter 77 group there. The case of Yuri Orlov in the USSR was raised and it was made clear that the British delegation would continue to campaign on these matters most firmly. All in all it was calculated and blunt - the intent being to clearly distance the British delegation from the socialist countries on issues of controversy in Western media. These participating nations would most certainly view the highly specific and selective statement as an intended insult in what was intended to be a Festival of friendship.

The eventual amended version put these points a little more in context. A firm distinction between those who are "genuinely committed to both détente and human rights, and those who are exploiting the issue of human rights for their own political advantage" was made. Moreover, the absence of some fundamental human rights in Britain was noted, especially with regard to Northern Ireland. It was recognised that human rights also involved some fairly fundamental economic rights and the exploitation of developing countries by the advanced capitalist nations (not specified as such however) was a pre-requisite to human rights in that part of the world.

The hypocrisy of the Western nations was thus signified in the revised statement. In particular, specific instances of abuses of human rights in the USA were mentioned, especially of black and indigenous American peoples. The original draft had called for the ending of racist political systems just in South Africa. This was implicitly widened to allow for the interpretation that this could apply to Britain also. The original had said that the delegation was opposed to particular imperialist interference from whatever quarter and this was softened to make it less an obviously contrived comment on the socialist as well as capitalist world. A positive note was also injected, linking anti-imperialist struggles throughout the world to the concrete solidarity organisations and actions traditionally associated with the British people. Criticisms of the USSR and South Africa had been made in the same breath, but were now separated and some positive features of Soviet life were incorporated, albeit that these were rather lamely highlighted. The previous condemnation of the Warsaw Pact intervention in 1968 in Czechoslovakia was turned into a statement of the fact that the intervention had been widely condemned in Britain. As was the criticism of the trial of Yuri Orlov, again, instead of the delegation being committed to condemn the USSR, it was observed that such criticisms had been made by some. While, finally, the previous commitment to campaigning on differences with the socialist world was eliminated.

The minority produced their own statement, on behalf of "a large percentage of the British delegation" they dissociated themselves from the majority statement, which they identified as being issued by the BPC - which it had not been, even in the first instance, let alone after amendment by the delegation. The minority statement complained that the majority statement did not "represent the views of the youth and students of Great Britain". Moreover that the BPC since its inception had not taken the "wide ranging opinions of the British youth into account". The exclusions were referred to and it was stated that the BPC had not "taken actions based on majority decisions either here (in Havana) or in Great Britain". The spirit of the Festival was endorsed by the statement, with the implication that a minority of the delegation, especially in leadership positions, had other axes to grind.

Not that this was the end of such controversies. Phillips, of course, made speeches and distributed leaflets of the statement. But the British delegation officially used its veto during one of the main debates against a Festival communiqué, stating that the capitalist countries were locked in a deepening economic crisis, from which the only escape could be profound political and social change. While women's liberationists distributed leaflets in Spanish, outlining their demands, which put attitudes to homosexuality that clashed sharply with the Cuban view then prevailing. (A more relaxed attitude now exists.) However, at no stage did the Cuban authorities or the World Preparatory Committee interfere with any of this. Other than a mild expression of displeasure by one of the Soviet representatives to Phillips at the discourtesy of the British delegation statement, there appears to have been only a feeling of bewilderment at the antics of the British by a number of delegations at the most and, at the least, a general lack of interest in what was largely an issue only for some on the British delegation.

In Britain however there was some interest. The Times, in an editorial, generally welcomed the British delegation's official position - arguing that even the split within the delegation must have been a lesson, though a puzzling one, on the freedom to disagree. While the East Midlands District Committee of the CPGB was more worried about the affair and wrote as much to the YCL EC. The latter however was not impressed by the lesson on the right to disagree. Two of its delegates to Havana, one of who was from the East Midlands, were "no longer to be allowed to represent the YCL at any outside event, due to events that took place in Havana". \[YCL EC Minutes 14th/15th October 1978\]  They had of course been associated with the minority statement.

Despite the trauma of these differences, the British involvement in the Festival had been positive and a wide degree of youth unity had been achieved around the ideas of world peace and friendship. Many cold war barriers had been broken down, but for some the question would naturally be posed - at what price for the YCL's own internal unity?

Organisations as disparate as the BYC, the NUS, NOLS, the British Council of Churches, the Student Christian Movement, the National Association of Youth Clubs, the Young Liberals, Quakers, the school students union (NUSS), AUEW-TASS, Young European Left and the YCL had agreed to the statement on Détente, Peace and Human Rights. It had been issued in their names, not the BPC, however. Even though the BPC continued its work for a short while after the Festival, the YCL was edgy about its continued existence and ensured that its influence was brought to bear in winding up the organisation.